(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-01T08:50:56.641414",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
暖かいな
It's so warm...
すごい。
Amazing.
あ、皆さん！
Ah, everyone!
お待たせしてます！こんばんはみおー！
Sorry to keep you waiting! Good evening, Mio!
大神みおのウクレレライブに、ようこそいらっしゃいました。
Welcome to Ookami Mio's Ukulele Live.
本日はですね、えー運営さんが気を利かせてですね、ロケーションを、このようになんか森っぽいロケーションでね、していただきましてありがとうございます。
Today, management was thoughtful enough to set this up in a forest-like location. Thank you so much!
今日は、こうみおファンの森に囲まれながら、ウクレレを披露したいなって思ってます。
Today, I want to perform the ukulele surrounded by Mio Fan Forest.
こんばんはみおー！
Good evening, Mio!
ごめんね、遅れちゃって30分。ちょっと前のお仕事が押してしまったんだよ。
Sorry I'm 30 minutes late. My previous work ran a bit over.
で、こんなね、ちょっと焚き火を、あのくべてくれてね、ちょっと寒いから焚き火の前がいいんじゃないかということで、
And they set up a campfire for us. Since it's a bit cold, they thought it'd be nice to be in front of the fire,
焚き火の前でね、今日はなんかこうちょっとキャンプをしながらウクレレを弾いてるような、そういう気持ちでやっていきたいと思います。
so we're doing it in front of the campfire with the feeling of camping while playing the ukulele.
あ、森は燃えてないですから、大丈夫です。これ はね、キャンプファイヤーでやってますからね、あの安全を確認した上でやってますので大丈夫ですよ。
Ah, the forest isn't burning, so it's fine. We're doing this as a campfire with safety confirmed, so don't worry!
はい、ありがと、みんな来てくれてありがとー！
Yeah, thank you! Thank you all for coming!
というわけでね、今日はなんと、こんなジャージャー、ちゃんとウクレレも召喚してもらってね。
So today, ta-da! They even summoned a proper ukulele for me.
これ でやっていきたいと思うんだけけれども、ちょっとね、あのうちは練習がてらね、チューニングをやてしまって、あ、いるので、今日はチューニングは省きたいと思います。みんな大好きなチューニングは、はい。
I'd like to use this, but as practice... wait, I already did the tuning, so I'll skip tuning today. Everyone's favorite tuning, yeah.
というわけで、さ、早速ウクレレライブ始めようと思うんだけども、
With that said, let's start the ukulele live right away.
ま、まずはね、あの、あ、最終的にウクレレ燃やすとかね、あ、ウクレレの、ウクレレがたまにウクレレなくなるんだけど、そういうあの、もんだと思ってください。はい。
Well, first, uh... think of it as something where the ukulele occasionally burns or disappears. Yeah.
というわけで、えーと、ウクレレライブ、え、まずは、えーと、一番最初に引いた、えー散歩をやってみて、
So, ukulele live! First, let's play 'Sanpo', the very first song I played,
ま、それでね、あの、試聴かんのみんなにね、あ、成長したなって思われたいなって思っておりますので、
and I hope you all watching will think, 'Oh, she's improved!'
あ、ウクレレたまに消えますが、みなさん気にせずに、えー、演奏を聞いていただければと思います。
Ah, the ukulele might occasionally vanish, but please don't mind it and just enjoy the performance.
ま、ちょっとね森の中でね聞いてるみたいなね、
Like you're listening to it deep in the forest...
感じで、はい。
Like this, yep.
これがな...
This is...
ちょっと、ちょっとあれだけど、ちょっと、ちょっと。
Wait, it's a bit... wait, wait.
どうしてもちょっとね、あんなちょ、あ、これがちょ、ちょうどいい、ちょうどいい。はい。
Somehow it's a bit... ah, this is just right, just right. Yep.
それでは、えー聞いてください。
Well then, um, please listen.
えーウクレレライブ1曲目は、
Um, for the first song of the ukulele live,
課題曲1曲目でした。えー、さんぽです。
it was the first assigned song, "Sanpo".
行きます。
Here we go.
あるこう あるこう わたしは元気
Let's walk, let's walk, I'm fine.
あるくの大好き どんどんいこう
I like to walk so let's go on.
坂道 トンネル 草っぱら
Hills, tunnels, grass,
一本橋に 凹凸砂利道
Bridges, and bumpy gravel roads.
蜘蛛の巣くぐって 下り道
Crawling under spider webs and downhill.
あるこう あるこう わたしは元気
Let's walk, let's walk, I'm fine.
あるくの大好き どんどんいこう
I like to walk so let's go on.
みつばち ぶんぶん 花畑
The honey bee buzzes in the flower field.
間違えた！
I messed up!
あるくの大好き
I like to walk,
どんどんいこう
so let's go on.
みつばち ぶんぶん...
Honey bee, buzz buzz...
花畑
flower field.
日向にとかげ へびはるね
A lizard in the shade, the snake napping.
ばったがとんで まがりみち
A grasshopper hops, the turning road.
さんぽでした。
That was "Sanpo".
ちょっと間違えちゃった。ちょっといつもと違う環境でウクレレを引くのは少し緊張しますね。
Playing ukulele in a different environment is a bit nerve-wracking.
ありがとうございます、試検官の皆さん。
Thank you very much, everyone on the examining board.
え、そして、ええと
Um, and, um...
やはりね、こないだ、あの、先週さ、覚えてる? 白日をさ、課題曲にしたじゃん。
You see, last week, remember? We made "Hakujitsu" the assigned song.
それも引いて、うちわみんなに、あの合格をもらなきゃいけないなって思ってるのよ。
I feel like I need everyone's approval on it too.
なんかみんなに、あの白日を聞いてもらおうかなって思います。2曲目は。
I think I'll have everyone listen to "Hakujitsu" for the second song.
というわけで、試検官のみんな、出番ですよ、皆さん。
So, everyone on the examining board, it's your turn.
うちのこの3Dの身体で白日引きますからね。
I'll play "Hakujitsu" with this 3D body of mine.
じゃ、ちょっと楽譜用意しますのでお待ちくださいね。
Well then, I'll prepare the sheet music, so please wait a moment.
はい、試検官の皆さん、準備はいいですか?
Alright, examining board everyone, are you ready?
白日は、ちょっとね、難しいんですけど、練習しましたので聞いてもらいたいと思います。
"Hakujitsu" is a bit difficult, but I practiced it so I'd like you to listen.
それでは、ちょっと間違えたら2回目引いてもいいっていうかもしれない。はい。
If I make a mistake, I might say it's okay to play it a second time. Yep.
はい、それでは行きます。白日。
Alright, here we go. "Hakujitsu".
時には誰かを 知らず知らずのうちに
Sometimes, without even realizing,
傷つけてしまったり 失ったりして初めて 犯した罪を知る
you hurt someone or lose them, and only then realize the sins you've committed.
戻れない、昔ようには 輝いて見えたとしても 明日へと歩き出さなきゃ
You can't go back like in the past. Even if it glitters, you must walk on towards tomorrow.
誰のために生きるなら
Someone to live for?
正しいことばかり
Just saying the right things
言ってらんないような
won't get you anywhere.
どこかの街で また出逢えたら
If we meet again in some town,
僕の名前を 覚えていますか
will you remember my name?
その頃にはきっと 春風が吹くだろう
A spring breeze is sure to be blowing then.
真っさらに生まれ変わって 人生一から始めようが
Living life anew, starting over from scratch,
へばりついて離れない
stuck and unable to break free,
地続きの今を歩いているんだ
walking through the present, stuck in place.
真っ白に全てさよなら 降りしきる
Bid it all farewell in pure white.
雪よ 全てを包み込んでくれ
Falling snow, wrap everything up.
今日だけは全てを隠してくれ
For today only, hide everything away.
ちょ、ちょっと待って。みんな、ちょっと待って、ちょっと待って。
Wait, wait. Everyone, wait a second.
もう一回、もう一回、もう一回チャンスください！
Please give me another chance!
もう一回チャンスください。試聴かんの皆さんお願いします！
Please, I'm begging you all, stream viewers!
お願いします！すいません！
I'm so sorry!
あの、ちょっ、あの、ポジションがな、ちょっと慣れない場所で引くか、
Um... my positioning was a bit...
ポジションがな、ちょっとポジションがうまく行かなかったな。いや、いいですか？すいません、あの
Is it okay? I'm sorry.
あー、すいません。あ、ありがとうございます。
Ah... I'm sorry.
すいません。ちょっと水も。
Sorry, let me get some water.
え、すごくない？なんか、みんなさ、
Isn't this amazing, everyone?
今日さ、キャンプファイヤーの前でウクレレを弾くっていう
Today, I'm playing the ukulele in front of the campfire...
こんな素朴な放送のために、3Dやらせてもらったんだよ、だよ。
They let me do this simple broadcast in 3D, like, really.
すいません、どうもありがとうございます。
Ahaha! Thanks so much.
すいません、お借りしております。
Sorry, I borrowed this.
「平日なら」とお借りしております。はい。
"For weekdays only," I've borrowed it. Yes.
では、白日もう一回行きたいと思います。
Well, I'd like to try "Hakujitsu" again.
はい。
Yes.
ちょっと緊張するな。テストだからね。
I'm a bit nervous since it's a test, you know.
行きます。
Here I go.
時には誰かを 知らず知らずのうちに
Sometimes, without even knowing it,
傷つけてしまったり 失ったりして初めて
hurting someone or losing them,
犯した罪を知る
you come to realize the sins you've committed.
戻れないよ、昔のようにさ
You can't go back to the way things were.
煌めいて見えたとしても
Even if it seemed to glimmer,
明日へと歩き出さないと
you have to step out toward tomorrow.
雪が降り頻ろうとも
Even if the snow keeps falling,
今の僕には 何ができるのか?
what can I do for you now?
何になれるのか?
What can I become?
誰のために生きるなら
If I'm living for someone,
正しいことばかり言ってらんないよな
I can't just keep saying the right things.
どこかの街で また出逢えたら
If we can meet again in some town,
僕の名前を 覚えていますか
will you remember my name?
その頃にはきっと 春風が吹くだろう
A spring breeze is sure to be blowing then.
今の僕には何ができるの? 何になれるの?
What can I do now? What can I become?
誰かのために 生きるん
If I'm living for someone,
なら 正しいことばかり言ってらんないような
just saying the right things won't get you anywhere.
どこかの街で また出逢えたら
If we meet again in some town,
僕の名前を 覚えていますか
will you remember my name?
その頃にはきっと 春風が吹くだろう
A spring breeze is sure to be blowing then.
真っさらに生まれ変わって 人生一から始めようが
Living life anew, starting over from scratch,
へばりついて離れない
stuck and unable to break free,
地続きの今を歩いてるんだ
walking through the present, stuck in place.
真っ白に全てさよなら 降りしきる
Bid it all farewell in pure white.
雪よ 全てを包み込んでくれ
Falling snow, wrap everything up.
今日だけは全てを隠してくれ
For today only, hide everything away.
ちょっとだけ間違えましたー。
I made just a tiny mistake.
どうですか、試験管の皆さん。
How was it, all you chemistry-tank viewers?
これが、うちが練習した。
This is what we practiced.
えーとね、この「白日」のね、あのね、最初のところは、
And you see, for this "Hakujitsu"...
えっと、ちょっぴり、あの、あの、工夫して弾くことにしたんです。
I decided to put a little extra effort into how I play it.
あ、あの、し、うし、あ、うし。そう、ちゃっがね、
Ah... "ushi"... "ushi"...
必要だということが分かったの。
I realized I needed it.
全部ね、同じテンポで弾く んじゃなくて、ちゃ、うしなったりって、
Instead of playing everything at the exact same tempo,
あ、あの、弾く場所をね、変えることによって、ちょっと、あの、メリハリがね、出るように工夫したりして
changing where I play it adds a bit of groove and expression.
どうですか、どうでしょう、みんなさん。
How's everyone doing?
合格、あ、試験官の皆さん！
To everyone who passed the exam!
いつもいつもお世話になっております。合格、あ、ありがとうございます。あ、
Thank you all so much for your continued support!
ちょっとじゃあ、ちょっと、そこでのこだわり部分だけ引かせてもらおう。
Let me just play a specific part of it.
広い宇宙の
In a vast universe,
数ある一つの
among countless others,
青い地球の
on a blue planet,
広い世界で小さなしの思いは届く小さな島のあなたのものへと
in this vast world...
あなたと出会い時間は流れる思いを込めた手紙も増える
meeting you, time flows on.
お、こ、こ、これです。
Alright, that's it!
あ、ありがとう。合格だって！ありがとうございます！
Thank you! Congratulations on passing!
試験官の皆さんいつもお世話になっております。
Examiners, thank you for your continued support!
というわけで、じゃあ今回もあの試験官の皆さんに合格をいただくことができたので、
So since everyone passed the exam this time, too,
じゃあ今までのえっと引いてきた合格曲をえ、引いていきたいなと思います。
I'd like to play the songs we've practiced so far.
はい。頑張ってる？ありがとうございます。
Are you doing your best? Thank you!
じゃあちょっとね、他の曲も行きたいと思います。じゃあちょっと練習したからね。
Let me practice a bit more since I've been practicing.
え、次はですね、え、スピッツさんの空も飛べるはず。
Next up is Spitz's "Sora mo Toberu Hazu".
これも練習曲でしたね。
This was also a practice song, right?
これを弾きたいと思います。今までのね、あの練習してき曲をね、順番に弾いていって、であとはうちが好きな曲を弾いたりとかしていこうかなって思ってます。
I want to play this in order, followed by other songs I like.
はい。それでは、え、空も飛べるはず。
So, "Sora mo Toberu Hazu".
幼い微熱を下げられないまま
Unable to bring down my still-immature slight fever,
神様の影を恐れて
I lived in fear of God's shadow.
隠したナイフが似合わない僕を
The knife I kept hidden on me didn't suit me at all,
おどけた歌でなぐさめた
yet it comforted me with a joking song.
色褪せながら ひび割れながら
As I felt myself fade in color, develop cracks all over,
輝くすべを求めて
I sought a way for me to shine.
君と出会った奇跡がこの胸にあふれている
The miracle of meeting you is overflowing from my chest.
きっと今は自由に空も飛べるはず
Now, I feel as though I could freely fly through the sky, surely.
夢を濡らした涙が海原へ流れたら
When the tears soaking my dreams flow towards the seabed,
ずっとそばで笑っていてほしい
that's when I want you to be by me, always smiling.
君と出会った奇跡がこの胸にあふれている
The miracle of meeting you is overflowing from my chest.
きっと今は自由に空も飛べるはず
Now, I feel as though I could freely fly through the sky, surely.
ゴミできらめく世界が僕たちを拒んでも
Even if we're shut out by a world glittering with garbage,
ずっとそばで笑っていてほしい
I want you always smiling beside me.
君と出会った奇跡がこの胸にあふれている
The miracle of meeting you is overflowing from my chest.
きっと今は自由に空も飛べるはず
Now, I feel as though I could freely fly through the sky, surely.
空も飛べるはず スピッツさんの曲でした。ありがとうございました。
"Sora mo Toberu Hazu", a song by Spitz. Thank you very much!
この曲は確か、えっと 試験官のみんなが最初のほうに散歩の次だったかな？空も飛べるはずを弾き語りでおすすめだよって言われて
I heard that "Sora mo Toberu Hazu" is recommended for learning the ukulele,
あ、いいかもしれないと思って それで選びました。
so I thought it might be good and chose it.
パチパチありがとう。
Pat-pat, thank you!
思い出の曲だね。次の曲いこうかな。
It's a song full of memories. Let's move on to the next song.
次の曲はじゃあな、
Well then, for the next song...
これにしようかな。
I think I'll go with this one.
これはちょっと最近の歌い曲なんだけど、
This is a somewhat recent song, but...
こないだのライブの前だね、月光。
just before the other day's live, Gekkou.
このね、月光の鬼束ちほろさんの曲もね、ちょっと好きな曲なので、弾いていこうと思います。
I really like this song "Gekkou" by Chihiro Onitsuka, so I thought I'd play it.
ちょっと強気?
A bit bold?
うちの子タブろうとしてるのかな? それともウクレレのことタブろうとしているのか?
Is my child trying to tab-out? Or trying to tab out the ukulele?
いや、大丈夫大丈夫。綺麗に囲ってある、し、キャンプファイヤーってこんなもんだろ。
No, it's fine. It's neatly enclosed, and campfires are like this.
それでは、えー鬼束ちほろさんの「月光」、いきます。
Well then, um, Chihiro Onitsuka's "Gekkou", here we go.
ああ神様 この腐敗した世界に堕とされた...
Ah, God, cast down into this decaying world...
って間違えた... すいませんもう一回！
Oops, I messed up... Sorry, one more time!
I am GOD'S CHILD この腐敗した世界に堕とされた
I am GOD'S CHILD, cast down into this decaying world.
How do I live on such a field?
こんなもののために生まれたんじゃない
I wasn't born for something like this.
突風に埋もれる足取り
Footsteps buried in the sudden gust,
倒れそうになるのを
about to fall over,
この鎖が 許さない
these chains won't allow it.
心を 開け放したままです
With my heart left wide open,
貴方の感覚だけが散らばって
only your senses scatter around.
私はまだ上手手に片付けられずに
I still can't tidy them away skillfully.
I am GOD'S CHILD 悲しい音は
I am GOD'S CHILD, sad sounds
背中に爪痕をつけて
leave scratch marks on my back.
I can't hang out this world
こんな思いじゃ どこにも居場所なんてない
with feelings like this, there's nowhere I belong.
不快に冷たい壁と壁とが...
Unpleasantly cold walls meeting walls...
次はどれに弱さを許す?
Which one will I show weakness to next?
終わりになど手を伸ばさないで
Don't reach out for an end;
貴方なら救い出して
if it's you, rescue me.
私を 静寂から
Rescue me from the silence.
時間は痛みを加速させて行く
Time only accelerates the pain.
I am GOD'S CHILD この腐敗した世界に
I am GOD'S CHILD, cast down
堕とされた
into this world.
How do I live on such a field?
こんなもののために生まれたんじゃない
I wasn't born for something like this.
I am GOD'S CHILD
おっとと... ウクレレくんの音が... すいません、ありがとうございます。
Whoa... the ukulele's sound... Sorry, thank you.
いつものとは違う環境だからね。
Because the environment is different from usual.
なぜかウクレレくんがどんどんツルツルツルツル左に動くんだよね。
For some reason, the ukulele keeps sliding to the left.
どうしたのかな、ウクレレくんも緊張しているのかな?
What's wrong, is the ukulele nervous too?
落ち着いて、大丈夫。大丈夫か?
Calm down, it's fine. Are you okay?
ほとんど左に行ってる、緊張しているの?
It's going mostly to the left, are you nervous?
ああっ、そっかそっかそっか... 緊張しているんだって！
Oh, I see, I see... It's nervous!
だからどんどん左に行きたくなっちゃうんだ。
That's why it keeps wanting to go to the left.
そうです
That's right.
どんどん勝手にずれられるとさ
When things keep getting out of sync on their own,
どんどん弾く場所がずれてくんだよ
the place where I play keeps shifting, you know.
はい、というわけで、えー月光、鬼束ちひろさんの曲でした。ありがとうございました。
Right, well, that was "Gekkou" by Chihiro Onitsuka. Thank you very much.
他にもね、課題曲いくつかりますよねー。
There are other assigned songs too, right?
夜空ノムコウにしようかな。ありましたよね、夜空ノムコウもね。
I wonder if I should do "Yozora no Mukou". There was "Yozora no Mukou" too, right?
ウクレレくんリラックスして、そうだよ。
Ukulele-kun, relax, that's right.
ウクレレくん、みんなもリラックスしてって言ってるよ。がんばって。
Ukulele-kun, I'm telling everyone to relax too. Do your best.
ウクレレくんもなるべく頑張るんだけど、初めてこう、ちゃんとした姿でみんなの前に出るのが恐ろしく緊張してるんだって。
Ukulele-kun is trying his best too, but he's super nervous about appearing in front of everyone properly for the first time.
みんな！ウクレレくんのことも応援してやってね。
Everyone! Please cheer for Ukulele-kun too.
では、えー夜空ノムコウを弾きたいと思います。
Well then, um, I'd like to play "Yozora no Mukou".
あれからぼくたちは
Since then, have we been able
何かを信じてこれたかな
to believe in something?
夜空の向こうには
Beyond the night sky,
明日はもう待っている
tomorrow is already waiting.
だれかの声に気づき ぼくらはいなをひそめた
Noticing someone's voice, we hid ourselves.
公園のフェンス越しに 夜の風が吹いた
Over the park fence, the night wind blew.
君が何か伝えようと 握りかえしたその手では ぼくの心の柔らかい場所を
The hand you gripped back trying to tell me something still grasps onto the soft part of my heart.
今でもまだしめつける
Even now, it still tightens.
あれからぼくたちは
Since then, have we been able
何かを信じてこれたかな
to believe in something?
窓をそっと開けてみる
Softly opening the window,
冬の風のにおいがした
I smelled the winter wind.
悲しみっていつかは
I wonder if sadness
消えてしまうものなのかな
is something that disappears over time.
ためいきは少しだけ
My sigh stayed white for a bit
白く残ってすぐ消えた
and suddenly disappeared.
あれからぼくたちは
Since then, have we been able
何かを信じてこれたかな
to believe in something?
夜空の向こうには
Beyond the night sky,
もう明日が待っている
tomorrow is already waiting.
夜空ノムコウでした。
That was "Yozora no Mukou".
メンバーシップいっぱい入ってくれてありがとうございます。
Thank you so much for joining the membership.
この曲もね、確か、夜空ノムコウも結構、まあ真ん中ぐらいに弾いた曲だったかな？
I think "Yozora no Mukou" was also a song I played somewhere in the middle, right?
えっと、E、E7、E7の...
Um, E, E7, E7's...
これですね。これがちょっと難しくて、E7むず...
This one. This is a bit difficult, E7 is hard...
難しいけど練習になるからこの曲にしようって思って
"It's difficult, but it's good practice, so I chose this song,"
E7がいっぱい出てくる
"and a lot of E7 chords come up."
この一曲を弾いたことにより、うちはいっぱいE7を克服しましたね。
"By playing this one song, I've really overcome E7 chords."
あ、メンバーシップありがとうね。
"Ah, thank you for the membership."
はい。じゃ、お次の曲いきたいと思います。
"Right. Well, I'd like to move on to the next song."
ええと、次はこのウクレレ曲の代表曲といっても過言ではない、「風になる」。
"Um, next is 'Kaze ni Naru', which is practically a staple ukulele song."
あ、ウクレレくん、
"Ah, Ukulele-kun,"
ウクレレくんいなくならないで。
"Ukulele-kun, please don't disappear."
よしよし、いこだね。
"There, there, good boy."
あ、E7克服曲で、え、風になるはすごく、あ、
"Ah, as an E7-conquering song, uh, 'Kaze ni Naru' is very—ah,"
ウクレレくん、ウクレレくん、頼むよ！ちょっと緊張してるかもしれないけど、頼むよ！
"Ukulele-kun, Ukulele-kun, please! I might be a little nervous, but please!"
もう、自らね、そんな薪になりに行かないでくださいよ。
"Don't go trying to become firewood yourself, please."
風になる、を弾きたいと思います。辻綾ノさんの曲です。
"I'd like to play 'Kaze ni Naru'. It's a song by Ayano Tsuji."
この曲はも元々ウクレレの曲なのでね、すごい元気で歌えるということでね、選びました。
"This song was originally written for the ukulele, so I chose it because I can sing it very cheerfully."
リズムもちょっと、今までのね、チョンチョンチョンチョンとはまたちょっと違うんですよね。
"The rhythm is also a bit different from the previous 'chon chon chon chon'."
はい。では、辻綾ノさんの「風になる」です。
"Alright. Now, Ayano Tsuji's 'Kaze ni Naru'."
忘れていた目を閉じて 取リ戻せ こいのうた
"Close the forgotten eyes and retrieve the love song"
青空に隠れている 手を伸ばしてもう一度
"Reach out your hand hidden in the blue sky one more time"
忘れないで すぐそばに僕がいる いつ 日も
"Don't forget, soon I'll be by your side all the time"
星空を眺めている 一人きりの夜明けも
"Even when at dawn you gaze at the starry sky alone"
たった一つの心 悲しみに暮れないで
"Don't let your only heart become darkened by sadness"
君のためいきなんて 春風に変えてやる
"I'll change your sighs into the spring breeze"
陽のあたる坂道を 自転車で駆けのぼる
"I ride my bike fast up the sunny hill"
君と失くした想い出乗せて行くよ
"Carrying the memories I lost with you"
ラララララ 口ずさむ くちびるを染めて行く
"Lalalalala, I hum, staining my lips"
君と見つけた幸せ 花のように
"The happiness I've found with you is like a flower"
君のためいきなんて 春風に変えてやる
"For your sake, I'll change your sighs into the spring breeze"
陽のあたる坂道を 自転車で駆けのぼる
"I ride my bike fast up the sunny hill"
君と失くした想い出乗せて行くよ
"Carrying the memories I lost with you"
ラララララ 口ずさむ くちびるを染めて行く
"Lalalalala, I hum, staining my lips"
君と見つけた幸せ 花のように
"The happiness I've found with you is like a flower"
ナナナナナ 口ずさむ くちびるを染めてゆく
"Nananana, I hum, staining my lips"
君と見つけた 幸せ 花のように
"The happiness I found with you is like a flower"
君と出逢えた 幸せ 祈るように
"Like praying for the happiness of meeting you"
風になる、辻綾ノさんの曲でした。
"That was 'Kaze ni Naru' by Ayano Tsuji."
こう軽快なね、ちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃちゃって言うのがね、あのすごくいい感じの曲ですね。ありがとうございます。
"It's a really upbeat song with that lively 'cha-cha-cha-cha-cha-cha' rhythm. Thank you."
じゃあ、次は、えっと、
"Well, next is, um,"
うん、でもこう、大体ね、これで終わりかな？もう他にないよね？これで、もう課題曲全部やったよね？
"Yeah, but, like, is this basically it? There aren't any others, right? With this, we've done all the assigned songs, right?"
いや、だいぶ上達したね。1ヶ月で、これだけ弾けるようになりました。嬉しい。
"Man, I've really improved. In one month, I'm able to play this much. I'm happy."
じゃ、次からは、えっと、うちが個人的に普通に好きな曲を弾いていきたいと思います。じゃ、ちょっとジブリシリーズで行こうかな。
"Well, from next, um, I'd like to play songs that I personally like. Let's go with the Ghibli series."
いや、本当にね、うちさ、全然さ、楽器弾けなくてさ、なんか弾き方やってみたいなって思って、ウクレレを始めてみたんだけど、ウクレレって結構ね、あの気軽に弾けるのでね、みんなもね、なんか難しそうだなってみる人もね、練習して...
"Man, really, you know, I couldn't play instruments at all, and I thought I'd try playing something, so I started the ukulele. But the ukulele is pretty casual to play, so everyone—even if you think it looks difficult, try practicing..."
あ、ウクレレくんがちょっと玉にイナクなるけど、ウクレレくん、頑張って、もうちょっと頑張って、頼むで！
"Ah, Ukulele-kun occasionally disappears, but Ukulele-kun, do your best, try a bit harder, please!"
ウクレレくんも、大体緊張はだいぶ溶けてきたみたいなんですけど、ちょっぴり集中力が切れてるみたいですね。はい（笑）。
"Ukulele-kun seems to have mostly melted away his nervousness, but it looks like his concentration is fading a bit. Yeah (laughs)."
でまあ、え、次はですね、え、ジブリの曲ちょっと続きまして、「いつも何度でも」、え、木村弓さんが歌ってるやつですね。あ、メンバーシップありがとう！
"And well, um, next is, uh, continuing with Ghibli songs, 'Itsumo Nando Demo', the one sung by Yumi Kimura. Ah, thank you for the membership!"
それでは、え、いきたいと思います。はい。
"Well then, uh, let's go. Right."
呼んでいる 胸のどこか奥で
"Somewhere, a voice calls, in the depths of my heart"
A voice is calling deep within my heart,
いつも心躍る 夢を見たい
I want to dream dreams that always make my heart race.
かなしみは 数えきれないけれど
Though my sorrows are too many to count,
その向こうできっと あなたに会える
I know I will surely meet you beyond them.
繰り返す あやまちの
With every repeated mistake,
そのたびひとは ただ青い
people only come to know the blue of the blue sky.
ただ青い空の 青さを知る
people only come to know the blue of the sky.
果てしない 道は続いて 見えるけれど
Though the endless road seems to stretch on,
この両手は 光を抱ける
these two hands can embrace the light.
さよならの ときの 静かな胸
In the quiet heart at the moment of farewell,
ゼロになるからだ 耳をすませる
my empty body listens closely.
生きている不思議 死んでいく不思議
The wonder of living, the wonder of dying,
花も風も街も みんな同じ
flowers, wind, and town are all the same.
ラララ… オオオ… ルルル…
La la la... Oh oh oh... Lu lu lu...
いつも何度でも でしたー
That was "Itsumo Nando Demo".
ちょっぴり 間違えちゃったけど
I messed up just a little bit though...
でも すごい いい曲ですね
Still, it's such a wonderful song.
じゃあ次は… 次の曲、えー、またジブリシリーズで
Now for the next... the next song, uh, continuing the Ghibli series,
「ひこうき雲」 来たいと思います
I'd like to perform "Hikoukigumo".
アパチパチありがとう！大丈夫？みんな
Clap clap, thank you! Are you all okay?
なんかね、あのね、ウクレレくん今日ツルツルする
You know, um, today Ukulele-kun is so slippery...
どんどん左に行ってしまうからね
It keeps sliding further and further to the left,
ウクレレくん今日どうしてツルツルなの？
Ukulele-kun, why are you so slippery today?
あ、そういうこと！なるほどね
Oh... I see! That makes sense.
ウクレレくん今日みんなに初めてこうやって姿を見られるから
Since Ukulele-kun is showing itself to everyone like this for the first time today,
体がツルツルになるくらいお風呂に入ってきたんだって
it took a bath until its whole body became slippery.
しょうがないね、それならね、ツルツルになるわけだ
Can't be helped then, of course it's slippery!
じゃあお次行きたいと思います。新井由美さんの「ひこうき雲」
Now let's move on to the next one. Yumi Arai's "Hikoukigumo".
白い坂道が空まで続いていた
The white slope continued on to the sky,
ゆらゆらかげろうが あの子を包む
and a wavering heat haze enveloped her.
誰も気づかず ただひとり
Unnoticed by anyone, all alone,
あの子は昇っていく
she ascends into the sky.
何もおそれない そして舞い上がる
She fears nothing and soars up high,
空に憧れて 空をかけてゆく
admiring the sky as she dashes through it.
あの子の命はひこうき雲
That girl's life is a vapour trail.
高いあの窓で あの子は死ぬ時も
At that high window, even before her death,
空を見ていた 今はわからない
she looked to the sky, though now we don't know,
ほかの人には わからない
other people don't understand.
あまりにも若すぎた とただ思うだけ
They only think she was far too young,
だけどしあわせ 空に憧れて
yet she is happy, admiring the sky,
空をかけてゆく あの子の命はひこうき雲
dashing through the sky—vapour trails are her life.
白い坂道が空まで続いていた
The white slope continued on to the sky
ゆれるかげろうが あの子を包む
A wavering heat haze envelops her
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
なんか…
Um...
どうした？
What's wrong?
うまくならなくなってきたな。
I feel like I'm getting worse at playing.
もう ちょっと疲れちゃったのかな。
I guess I'm getting a bit tired.
早いな。
That was fast.
いつもはね、大体1時間半から2時間ぐらい引いててもなんか…
Usually, even if I play for an hour and a half to two hours...
切ろうとしてるんだけど、やっぱり屋外で弾くとちょっぴりね、あの…
I try to keep going, but playing outdoors makes it a bit... um...
あ、パチパチありがとう。
Ah, thanks for the claps.
なんか、え、何？いってことあるって？あ、そう。
Wait, what? There's something you want to say? Oh, I see.
あ、なるほど、うんうんうんうん。あ、そうなんだ、ごめんね。
Ah, I see, yeah. Oh, is that so? Sorry.
そんな気遣いできなくてね。
I couldn't be that considerate.
花粉症なんだって。
She says she has hay fever.
だから、屋外だとちょっとね、あの、音がね、かすれちゃうみたい。
So outdoors, it seems the sound gets a bit raspy.
しょうがないね、それは。今、花粉いっぱい飛んでるみたいだからさ。
It can't be helped. It seems there's a lot of pollen flying right now.
しょうがないよね。今、花粉症の人大変だよね。
It can't be helped. People with hay fever have it tough right now.
うちは花粉症じゃないから ちょっとわかりにくいんだけど。
I don't have hay fever, so it's a bit hard to understand.
ウクレレくんちょっと花粉症なんだって。で、いつもは家にいるから大丈夫なんだけど、換気扇じゃねや、空気清浄機も炊いてるしね。
Ukulele-kun has hay fever. Usually, he's at home so it's fine, plus we have an air purifier running.
しょうがないね、それな。ちょっとかすれちゃうんだって。ちょっと、すみませんね、皆さんね。
It can't be helped. It gets a bit raspy. Sorry about that, everyone.
ちょっと今度は森でやらないように気をつけいあげないといけないかもしれないね。
Maybe next time I should be careful not to do it in the forest.
ごめんね、そんな花粉症の中来てくれてありがとね、うんうん。
Sorry, and thanks for coming despite the hay fever, yeah.
じゃ次行こうかな。
Well, let's go to the next one.
お次はスピッツさんのロビンソンを弾きたいと思います。
Next, I'd like to play Spitz's "Robinson".
頑張れ！
Do your best!
花粉症に森はきつい、そりゃそうだ。
A forest is tough for hay fever, of course it is.
頑張ってくれてますよ、ウクレレくんもね。
Ukulele-kun is trying his best too.
それでは、えー、聞いてください。スピッツさんのロビンソン、弾きたいと思います。
Well then, please listen. I'd like to play Spitz's "Robinson".
新しい季節は なぜかせつない日々で
The new season is for some reason filled with wistful days
河原の道を自転車で 走る君を追いかけた
I chased you riding a bicycle down the riverbank road
思い出のレコードと 大げさなエピソードを
Carrying a record of memories and an exaggerated episode
疲れた肩にぶら下げて しかめつら まぶしそうに
on my tired shoulders, squinting as if it were dazzling
同じセリフ 同じ時思わず口にするような
Saying the same lines, the same time, almost instinctively
ありふれたこの魔法で つくりあげたよ
I created with this ordinary magic
誰も触られない 二人だけの国君の手を離さぬように
In a world for just the two of us that no one can touch, so I won't let go of your hand
大きな力で 空に浮かべたら
If we float up into the sky with a great power
ルララ 宇宙の風に乗る
Lulala, riding the winds of space
待ち焦がれた夢のほりえ 驚いた君の瞳
The moat of the dream I eagerly awaited, your surprised eyes
そして僕ら今ここで 生まれ変わるよ
And now we are reborn right here
誰も触られない 二人だけの国終わらない歌ばらまいて
Scattering an endless song across a world for just the two of us
大きな力で 空に浮かべたら
If we float up into the sky with a great power
ルララ 宇宙の風に乗る
Lulala, riding the winds of space
大きな力で 空に浮かべたら
If we float up into the sky with a great power
ルララ 宇宙の風に乗る
Lulala, riding the winds of space
大きな力で 空に浮かべたら
If we float up into the sky with a great power
ルララ 宇宙の風に乗る
Lulala, riding the winds of space
ロビンソンでした。
That was Robinson.
じゃないか、ウクレレ頑張ったね。
That went well, you did your best with the ukulele.
じゃあ、えー、あとですね、残り2曲引いて終わりにしたいと思います。
Well, um, after this, I'd like to play two more songs and wrap things up.
あ、パチパチありがとう！
Ah, clap clap, thank you!
じゃあ次は、えーっとどれにしようかな。
Let's see, um, which one should I do next?
あいみょんさんの「マリーゴールド」弾きたいと思います。
I'd like to play Aimyon's "Marigold".
ちょっとお水飲む。
Let me drink some water.
あっという間だった？
Was it over in a flash?
あっという間だったね。
It really was over in a flash.
ウクレレもこんな森の中でね、花粉症なのに良く頑張ってくれたよね。
Even the ukulele, out here in the woods, with my hay fever and all, really did its best.
いや、今日は発表会なんできね、いろんな曲弾こうと思って持ってきてます。
Well, since it's a recital today, I brought a bunch of different songs to play.
では、マリーゴールドいきたいと思います。
Well then, let's go with "Marigold".
風の強さがちょっと
The strength of the wind
心を揺さぶりすぎて
sort of rattled my heart around too much,
真面目に見つめた
and I stared straight at you,
君が恋しい
longing for you.
でんぐり返しの日々
Through topsy-turvy days,
可哀想なふりをして
putting on a pitiful act,
だだこねてみたけれど
I threw a tantrum, but
希望の光は
the light of hope
目の前でずっと輝いている
is shining right before my eyes.
幸せだ
It's happiness.
麦わらの帽子の君が
You in your straw hat
揺れたマリーゴールドに似ている
look like swaying marigolds.
あれは空がまだ青い夏のこと
That was back when the sky was still a blue summer,
懐かしいと笑えたあの日の恋
a love of those days we could smile at with nostalgia.
「もう離れないで」と
Staring at you with tearful eyes
泣きそうな目でみつめる君を
saying, "Don't ever leave me,"
雲のような優しさでそっとぎゅっと
I'll gently and tightly hold you,
抱きしめて 抱きしめて 離さない
hold you, and never let you go.
ああ アイラブユーの言葉じゃ足りないからとキスして
Ah, because "I love you" isn't enough words, kiss me,
雲がまだ2人の影を残すから
since the clouds still leave our shadows behind,
いつでも いつでもこのまま
let's stay like this forever and ever,
話さない
and never let go.
マリーゴールドでした。
That was "Marigold".
ちょっとあまりミスなく弾けたので、ちょっと嬉しいです。
I managed to play it with hardly any mistakes, so I'm pretty happy.
ありがとう！
Thank you!
メンバーシップも入ってくれてる人、ありがとう！
Thank you to everyone who joined the membership too!
パチパチありがとうございます。
Thank you very much for the claps.
では、最後の曲いきたいと思います。
Well then, I'd like to go to the final song.
皆さんにね、あの、こんな森の中、ノスタルジックな気持ちで終わりにしたいなって思いますのでね。
I'd like to wrap things up with a nostalgic feeling here in the woods for you all.
パチパチありがとう。本当に上手になった、本当に？嬉しいな。
Clap clap, thank you. Have I really gotten better? Really? I'm so glad.
では、最後の1曲は、えー、Hello Again、昔からある場所、ま、おうちからね、よくね、好きでね、歌ってる曲なんだけれども。この曲を歌って終わりにしようと思います。メンバーシップありがとうね！
Well then, the final song is "Hello Again", a song I really love and often sing from home. I'll sing this to wrap up. Thank you for the membership!
はい、ではノスタルジックな気持ちで行きます。
Yes, now I'll go with a nostalgic feeling.
マイリトルラバーさんの曲です。
It's a song by My Little Lover.
いつも 君と 待ち続けた 季節は
The seasons we always waited for together
何も言わず 通り過ぎた
passed by without a word.
雨はこの街に 降り注ぐ
Rain pours down onto this town,
少しの リグレットと罪を 包み込んで
wrapping up a little regret and guilt,
泣かないことを 誓ったまま 時間は過ぎ
as time passed while I vowed not to cry,
痛む心に 気付かずに 僕は一人になった
and without noticing my aching heart, I became alone.
いつも 君と 待ち続けた
The seasons we waited for so long together
季節は 何も言えず 通り過ぎた
passed by without a word.
雨は この街に 降り注ぐ
Rain pours down on this town,
少しの リグレットと 罪を 包み込んで
wrapping up a few regrets and sins.
泣かないことを 誓ったまま 時は過ぎ
Time passed as I swore not to cry,
いたむ心に 気付かずに 僕はひとりになった
and I ended up all alone, unaware of my aching heart.
「記憶の中で ずっと二人は 生きていける」
"In our memories, the two of us can live on forever."
君の声が 今も胸に 響くよ
Your voice still echoes in my heart.
それは 愛が彷徨う影
It's the wandering shadow of love.
君は少し泣いた? あの時見えなかった
Did you cry a little? I couldn't see back then.
自分の限界が どこまでかを 知るために
I'm not living just to find out
僕は生きているわけじゃない
where my limits lie.
だけど 新しい扉を開け 海に出れば
But if I open a new door and head out to the sea,
波の彼方に ちゃんと“果て”を感じられる
I can truly feel the "end" beyond the waves.
Hello, again a feeling heart
Hello, again my old dear place
ハローエイゲン、昔からある場所、マイリトルラバーさんの曲でした。ありがとうございました。
"Hello, Again ~Mukashi kara aru Basho~" by My Little Lover. Thank you!
いやあ、というわけで、まあ計10曲ぐらいかな、引き切ったと思うんですけれども、
Well then, I think I've played around 10 songs in total,
え、うちがね、ウクレレを挑戦し続けて、もう早1か月ちょっとですね。
and it's been a little over a month since I started challenging the ukulele.
ようやくここまでたどり着けたが、もっともっとうまくなりたいと思いますので、これからもウクレレを弾く放送は続けていきたいなと思っています。
I want to get even better, so I plan to keep doing ukulele streams.
はい、どうもありがとうございました。
Yes, thank you very much!
ちょっとこの後に、あのね、もっと弾きたいんだけど、えっと、実はこの後に放送があって、あの、スモークの放送があって、
I wanted to play more, but there's a Smoke broadcast coming up,
あの、スモークの4人でね、あのゲームをやるので、あのそれをにのためにうちのちょうど帰らなければいけないということで、あのね、こんな森林の中まで来たんですけどね。
and since the four of us are playing games, I had to come out to this forest.
それにしてもこの森のロケーションすごいですね。なんか本当に、なんなんだろう、こんなとかあったっけ? なんか、初めてですよね。
Even so, this forest location is amazing. Is this my first time here?
何これ? え? 何これ? 何この仕切り? え?
What is this? Huh? What's this partition?
何? 駐車場? え? 海じゃん。
What? A parking lot? Huh? It's the ocean!
ウクレレ始めて1ヶ月ちょっと… 3Dウクレレ発表会
[Title: Ukulele 1 Month In... 3D Ukulele Recital]